<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="38"><page Index="1"/><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Covering the Latest Syllabus in Computer Education

                                         based on Windows Curriculum

                                                             By


                                              V. SAMSON PRAKASH

                                                        Director

                                      UNIQUE SOFTWARE SOLUTIONS


                             SAMSEL Publications



                              # 44, 2nd Floor, Taylor’s Road, Kilpauk, Chennai - 600 010.
                                      Phone: 044- 26474736 / 26454598 / 42857186
                                             Email: usssamsel@yahoo.co.in

                                    A unit of  U S S UNIQUE SOFTWARE SOLUTIONS]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[It goes without saying that Computers have become an integral part of our daily life. Technology
             Growth is at a faster pace and the need for learning the technology at an early age has become a
             necessity.

             In most schools computers have already paved its way,  as part of the regular curriculum.  At
 First Edition 2014
 Revised Edition 2015  present the stage is set to abreast with the fast growing pace of technology.
 Reprint - 2016  To fulfill the requirements of the present scenario, we at SAMSEL  bring to you the i-whizz ICT
 Reprint - 2017  computer books at School level graded VI to IX. This new multicolour series is based on
 Reprint - 2018  Windows Environment and focused purely on practical concepts with ample Activity based
 SAMSEL’S ©  exercises and Lab sessions.

 i-whizz series  Great care has been taken to elucidate the concepts and present it in a lively manner, in simple

 Information & Communication Technology  and lucid style with Multicolour Graphics, Suitable Illustrations, Exercises and Activities.

 Standard - VI  The contents include Computer Fundamentals and Windows Operating System in order to bring
             familiarity with the latest technology developments. MS Office 2007 package @ various Levels
 © Reserved  covering MS Word, PowerPoint and Excel concepts are dealt in a detailed manner supported by

             MS Office 2007 actual screenshots along with suitable illustrations and try in your lab activities.
             QBASIC, a programming language is also dealt in this series in order to enable children to
             develop problem solving abilities and learn its techniques. We have also dealt with animation
             package Flash and designing package Photoshop in this series.

             The 'Do You Know' concepts and 'Hint' are added features to give more wider knowledge of the
             concepts dealt here.

             The overwhelming response for our titles gained over the years has encouraged us to bring this
 Published by  new series. We hope that you find the learning process more interesting and enjoyable as the
 SAMSEL Publications  subject flow is simple and self-explanatory.
 # 44, 2nd Floor, Taylor’s Road
 Kilpauk, Chennai - 600 010.  I would like to gratefully acknowledge for the guidance and assistance provided by the editorial
 Ph: 044-26474736, 42857186   board of SAMSEL  and teaching staff of Unique Software Solutions in bringing this book to its
 Email: usssamsel@yahoo.co.in  present form.
 A unit of  U S S UNIQUE SOFTWARE SOLUTIONS
             We wish to continue this series with other books in the series which would enable the art of fun

             along with education and hope to achieve our mission at SAMSEL        'to educate every child and
             no one be left behind'.
             Suggestions for improvement of these books from teachers and readers are most welcome.
 Rs.130/-





             V. SAMSON PRAKASH

 © All rights reserved. No part of this publication may be reproduced or distributed in any form or by any
 means or stored in a database or retrieval system without prior permission of the publisher.]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[CH
                                                                        CHAPTER 1APTER 1

                                         Computer Fundamentals
 Contents
 C Coonntteennttss  Introduction



           Computer is an electronic data processing machine capable of performing millions of
           operations with tremendous speed.  It has the capacity of storing large volume of data,
           which can be used in future. Computer only follows the instructions given by the user,
           without any strain, self-thinking or reasoning. With the above qualities, Computer can be

           used in almost all fields.
 1  Computer Fundamentals  5  Computer consists of three main units namely



                                        (i)  Input Unit
 2  Introduction to Windows 7  18
                                        (ii) Central Processing Unit


 3  MS Word 2007     29                 (iii) Output Unit

           INPUT UNIT

 4  Formatting in MS Word 2007  39  The Input unit is a means of communication between the computer and the user.   To
           solve any problem, a set of instructions and data are fed into the computer through this

           unit.  These  instructions  are  converted  into  a  series  of  electronic  pulses,  which  the
 5  Advanced Word Processing  49  computer can understand and later sent to the Central Processing Unit. Some of the
           commonly used input devices are Keyboard and Mouse.


 6  Programming Fundamentals  CENTRAL PROCESSING UNIT

 using QBasic  56  It is in this unit that the entire work is done. It takes information from the input unit,

           processes them according to the instructions that the computer has received and then
           the processed data is sent to the output unit. CPU is also called as the brain of the
 7  QBasic Commands  64  computer.  This unit consists of three sub-units namely

                                        (i)  Memory Unit (MU)


                                        (ii) Control Unit (CU)

                                        (iii) Arithmetic and Logic Unit (ALU)


           OUTPUT UNIT

           This unit gives out the processed data (result) in user readable form.   Some of the
           commonly used output devices are monitor, printer, speaker, plotter and projector.  The
           result seen on the monitor is referred as Softcopy and the result got in the printed form

           on a paper is referred as Hardcopy.

                                                                                                              5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS                                                             C             ICT
                                                                 C
                                                                                                                                                                       COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS



            How does a Computer work?                                                                                                   RAMRAM

            The working principle of computer can be explained with the help of a block diagram,                                       RAM stands for Random Access Memory. This is a temporary
            as the internal structure of the machine cannot be drawn.                                                                  memory since the information stored in it is lost, when the
                                                             ALU                                                                       power is switched off. Hence it is called as volatile memory.
                                                                                                                                       There are three types of RAM namely,


                                                                                                                                                       1.  Dynamic Random Access Memory (DRAM)

                           INPUT                        MEMORY                         OUTPUT                                                          2.  Static Random Access Memory (SRAM)
                                                                                                                                                       3.  Complementary Metal Oxide Semi conductor (CMOS)

                                                                                                                                        ROMROM                       ROM stands for  ead  nly  emory. The information stored in
                                                                                                                                                                                        R
                                                                                                                                                                                                     M
                                                                                                                                                                                               O
                                                       CONTROL                                                                                                       this memory is permanent in nature and is not erased even
                                                                                                                                                                     when the power goes off. Hence it is called as non-volatile
                                                 Block diagram of a Computer
                                                                                                                                                                     memory. The information stored in this memory is written by
            After  receiving  the  data  from  the  input  unit,  the  processing  is  carried  out  by  the                                                         the  manufacturers.  There  are  three  types  of  ROM  namely,
            sub-units  of CPU.                                                                                                                                       PROM   , EPROM    and EAROM    .


             CONTROL UNITONTROL UNIT
             C                                                                                                                         PROM
                                                                                                                                       In  rogrammable  ead  nly  emory, a programmer can permanently store programs P  R  O  M
                                                                                                                                       into this chip thus it is varied from ROM, whereas in ROM it cannot be programmed but
                                                                                                                                       instead the program is burnt into the chip by the manufacturer himself.

                                                                                                                                       EPROM

                                                                                                                                                                         R
             ARITHMETIC AND LOGIC UNIT                                                                                                 In  rasable  rogrammable  ead  O            nly  M emory,  we  can  erase  the program  already
                                                                                                                                           E
             ARITHMETIC AND LOGIC UNIT
                                                                                                                                                      P
                                                                                                                                       stored in the chip and later a new program can be programmed on the same chip. It can
            This unit performs arithmetic calculations and logical operations. All  data are sent here
            for processing and after manipulation, the control unit directs the result to memory unit.                                 be erased by removing the chip from the circuit board and exposing it under ultraviolet
                                                                                                                                       rays for a few minutes. The program in EPROM is permanent in nature until it is erased
            This unit consists of accumulators and registers.
                                                                                                                                       and hence it is non-volatile.
            Accumulator stores the results of mathematical calculations temporarily till the control
            unit gives the transfer instruction.                                                                                       EAROM

            Registers are small memory of CPU which stores digital information.                                                        Electrically  Alterable  Read   Only   Memory is similar to that of EPROM except that it can
             ME                                                                                                                        be  re-programmed  without  removing  the  chip  from  the  circuit  board  i.e.  it  can  be
             MEMORY UNITMORY UNIT
                                                                                                                                       re-programmed electrically by a matter of milliseconds. The advantage of EAROM is that it
                                                                                                                                       can be re-programmed partially or completely which is not possible in the case of EPROM.
                                                                                                                                       UNITS OF MEMORY


                                                                                                                                       As solids are measured in grams and kilograms, liquids are measured in millilitres and

                                                          1) RAM                                                                       litres, computer's memory is measured in Bytes. A Byte is made up of 8 bits. A bit is a
                                                                                                                                       Binary Digit which represents 0 or 1.
                                                          2) ROM

              6                                                                                                                                                                                                                           7]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[ICT
 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS  C           ICT
 C
                                          COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS



 How does a Computer work?  RAMRAM

 The working principle of computer can be explained with the help of a block diagram,   RAM stands for Random Access Memory. This is a temporary
 as the internal structure of the machine cannot be drawn.  memory since the information stored in it is lost, when the
 ALU       power is switched off. Hence it is called as volatile memory.
           There are three types of RAM namely,


                          1.  Dynamic Random Access Memory (DRAM)

 INPUT  MEMORY  OUTPUT    2.  Static Random Access Memory (SRAM)
                          3.  Complementary Metal Oxide Semi conductor (CMOS)

           ROMROM                        ROM stands for  ead  nly  emory. The information stored in
                                                            R
                                                                         M
                                                                   O
 CONTROL                                 this memory is permanent in nature and is not erased even
                                         when the power goes off. Hence it is called as non-volatile
 Block diagram of a Computer
                                         memory. The information stored in this memory is written by
 After  receiving  the  data  from  the  input  unit,  the  processing  is  carried  out  by  the   the  manufacturers.  There  are  three  types  of  ROM  namely,
 sub-units  of CPU.                      PROM   , EPROM    and EAROM    .


 CONTROL UNITONTROL UNIT
 C         PROM
           In  rogrammable  ead  nly  emory, a programmer can permanently store programs P  R  O  M
           into this chip thus it is varied from ROM, whereas in ROM it cannot be programmed but
           instead the program is burnt into the chip by the manufacturer himself.

           EPROM

                                             R
 ARITHMETIC AND LOGIC UNIT  In  rasable  rogrammable  ead  O nly  M emory,  we  can  erase  the  program  already
              E
 ARITHMETIC AND LOGIC UNIT
                          P
           stored in the chip and later a new program can be programmed on the same chip. It can
 This unit performs arithmetic calculations and logical operations. All  data are sent here
 for processing and after manipulation, the control unit directs the result to memory unit.   be erased by removing the chip from the circuit board and exposing it under ultraviolet
           rays for a few minutes. The program in EPROM is permanent in nature until it is erased
 This unit consists of accumulators and registers.
           and hence it is non-volatile.
 Accumulator stores the results of mathematical calculations temporarily till the control
 unit gives the transfer instruction.   EAROM

 Registers are small memory of CPU which stores digital information.  Electrically  Alterable  Read  Only  Memory is similar to that of EPROM except that it can
 ME        be  re-programmed  without  removing  the  chip  from  the  circuit  board  i.e.  it  can  be
 MEMORY UNITMORY UNIT
           re-programmed electrically by a matter of milliseconds. The advantage of EAROM is that it
           can be re-programmed partially or completely which is not possible in the case of EPROM.
           UNITS OF MEMORY


           As solids are measured in grams and kilograms, liquids are measured in millilitres and

 1) RAM    litres, computer's memory is measured in Bytes. A Byte is made up of 8 bits. A bit is a
           Binary Digit which represents 0 or 1.
 2) ROM

 6                                                                                                            7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                                                 C                                                                                                     C             ICT
                                                                                                                                                                       COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS



                                                                                                                                        Mouseouse
                                             CHART OF MEMORY MEASUREMENT                                                                M

                               4 Bits                          =     1 Nibble                                                          A Mouse     is an input device. When we click on the button, the
                               8 Bits                          =     1 Byte                                                            mouse sends information to the computer. It is an alternative way
                               1024 Bytes                      =     1 Kilo Byte (KB)                                                  to interact with the computer besides a keyboard. When the user
                               1024 KB                         =     1 Mega Byte (MB)                                                  moves the mouse, the mouse pointer also moves in the screen. The

                               1024 MB                         =     1 Giga Byte (GB)                                                  different types of mice are scroll mouse, optical mouse, wireless mouse etc.
                                                                                                                                        Scannercanner
                               1024 GB                         =     1 Tera Byte (TB)                                                   S                       Scanner is an input device that is used to read/scan images
                               1024 TB                         =     1 Peta Byte (PB)                                                                           or  text  and  convert  them  to  digital  form.  It  creates  an
                               1024 PB                         =     1 Exa Byte (EB)                                                                            electronic version of the document that can be viewed and
                               1024 EB                         =     1 Zetta Byte (ZB)                                                                          edited on the computer. There are many different types of
                               1024 ZB                         =     1 Yotta Byte (YB)                                                                          scanners available based on the size, cost, clarity etc. One of

                               1024 YB                         =     1 Bronto Byte (BB)                                                                         the most commonly used scanner is flat bed scanner.
                               1024 Bronto Byte                =     1 Geon Byte (GB)
                                                                                                                                        W
                                                                                                                                        Web Cameraeb Camera
            INPUT DEVICES                                                                                                              Web camera is commonly called webcam. Webcam is an input device

            An input device      is the device that is used to input data to the computer. An input unit                               which is used to capture images. Webcam is the combination of web and

            takes the input and converts it into binary form so that it can be understood by the                                       video camera. It is mainly used in online chatting, video conferencing,
            computer. Some of the commonly used input devices are keyboard, mouse, scanner,                                            videos, still photographs and broadcast them on the web.
            digital camera, joystick and touch screen.                                                                                  J
                                                                                                                                        Joystickoystick
             Keyboardeyboard                                                                                                                                    Joystick  is  a  popular  input  device.
             K
                                                                                                                                                                Joysticks are often used to control video
            Keyboard  is  the  most  commonly  used
                                                                                                                                                                games and have one or more push buttons
            input device which is used to enter data in
                                                                                                                                                                whose state can be read by the computer.
            to the computer. It consists of typewriter
                                                                                                                                        Touch Screenouch Screen
            like  keys  to  enter  data.  Computer                                                                                      T
            keyboards  are  similar  to  electronic
                                                                                                                                       Touch screen is an input device that allows the user to operate PC by
            typewriter keyboard with some additional                               Standard Keyboard                                   simply touching the display in the screen region such as icons or graphical
            keys.
                                                                                                                                       buttons. The touch screen enables the user to interact directly with what
                                                The  keyboard        detects  the  key  pressed  and  generates
                                                                                                                                       is displayed, rather than using a mouse or any other intermediate device.
                                                the  corresponding  ASCII  code  which  is  recognized  by
                                                                                                                                       Touch  screen  monitors  have  become  very  popular  as  their  price  has
                                                computer. There are different types of keyboards such as
                                                                                                                                       steadily dropped when compared to the ones in the last decade.
                                                standard  keyboard,  multimedia  keyboard,  internet
                                                                                                                                       OU
                                                keyboard, wireless keyboard, Blue-tooth keyboard etc.                                  OUTPUT DEVICESTPUT DEVICES
                                                                                                                                       The output devices help us to see the final result. Any device that outputs information
                                                                               O
                                                                   DO  Y U  KNOW?                                                      from a computer is called an output device. Example of output devices include
                                                                                                                                                     Monitor, Printer, Speaker, Plotter, Projector, Headphone
                                                                    The QWERTY layout in
                Multimedia Keyboard                             the keyboard was invented by                                           But the most commonly used output devices are monitors, speakers and printers.
              8                                                       Christopher Sholes.                                                                                                                                                 9]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                         ICT
 C
 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS  COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                          C



            Mouseouse
 CHART OF MEMORY MEASUREMENT  M

 4 Bits  =  1 Nibble  A Mouse  is an input device. When we click on the button, the
 8 Bits  =  1 Byte  mouse sends information to the computer. It is an alternative way
 1024 Bytes  =  1 Kilo Byte (KB)  to interact with the computer besides a keyboard. When the user
 1024 KB  =  1 Mega Byte (MB)  moves the mouse, the mouse pointer also moves in the screen. The

 1024 MB  =  1 Giga Byte (GB)  different types of mice are scroll mouse, optical mouse, wireless mouse etc.
            S
 1024 GB  =  1 Tera Byte (TB)  Scannercanner  Scanner is an input device that is used to read/scan images
 1024 TB  =  1 Peta Byte (PB)       or  text  and  convert  them  to  digital  form.  It  creates  an
 1024 PB  =  1 Exa Byte (EB)        electronic version of the document that can be viewed and
 1024 EB  =  1 Zetta Byte (ZB)      edited on the computer. There are many different types of
 1024 ZB  =  1 Yotta Byte (YB)      scanners available based on the size, cost, clarity etc. One of

 1024 YB  =  1 Bronto Byte (BB)     the most commonly used scanner is flat bed scanner.
 1024 Bronto Byte  =  1 Geon Byte (GB)
            Web CameraWeb Camera
 INPUT DEVICES  Web camera is commonly called webcam. Webcam is an input device

 An input device  is the device that is used to input data to the computer. An input unit   which is used to capture images. Webcam is the combination of web and

 takes the input and converts it into binary form so that it can be understood by the   video camera. It is mainly used in online chatting, video conferencing,
 computer. Some of the commonly used input devices are keyboard, mouse, scanner,   videos, still photographs and broadcast them on the web.
 digital camera, joystick and touch screen.  J
            Joystickoystick
 K
 Keyboardeyboard                    Joystick  is  a  popular  input  device.
                                    Joysticks are often used to control video
 Keyboard  is  the  most  commonly  used
                                    games and have one or more push buttons
 input device which is used to enter data in
                                    whose state can be read by the computer.
 to the computer. It consists of typewriter
           T
 like  keys  to  enter  data.  Computer   Touch Screenouch Screen
 keyboards  are  similar  to  electronic
           Touch screen is an input device that allows the user to operate PC by
 typewriter keyboard with some additional   Standard Keyboard  simply touching the display in the screen region such as icons or graphical
 keys.
           buttons. The touch screen enables the user to interact directly with what
 The  keyboard   detects  the  key  pressed  and  generates
           is displayed, rather than using a mouse or any other intermediate device.
 the  corresponding  ASCII  code  which  is  recognized  by
           Touch  screen  monitors  have  become  very  popular  as  their  price  has
 computer. There are different types of keyboards such as
           steadily dropped when compared to the ones in the last decade.
 standard  keyboard,  multimedia  keyboard,  internet
           OUTPUT DEVICESTPUT DEVICES
 keyboard, wireless keyboard, Blue-tooth keyboard etc.   OU
           The output devices help us to see the final result. Any device that outputs information
 DO  Y U  KNOW?  from a computer is called an output device. Example of output devices include
 O
                         Monitor, Printer, Speaker, Plotter, Projector, Headphone
 The QWERTY layout in
 Multimedia Keyboard  the keyboard was invented by  But the most commonly used output devices are monitors, speakers and printers.
 8  Christopher Sholes.                                                                                       9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                     ICT
                                                                 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                                                                                                                                                       C
                                                                 C                                                                                                     COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS



                                                                                                                                        LCD MonitorD Monitor (Liquid Crystal Display)
              MONITOR                                                                                                                   LC

            The monitor     is an output device used to display the result.  It is also called as Screen or                            LCD monitor use ccfl back lights which contain Mercury. LCD
            Visual Display Unit (VDU).  The monitors are of two types                                                                  monitors  are  much  thinner,  lighter,  use  less  energy  and

                                                                                                                                       provide a greater graphics quality compared to CRT monitors.
                                                                                                                                        LED MonitorED Monitor (Light Emitting Diode)
                                                                                                                                        L




                                                                                                                                                                       LED monitor is basically the new version of
                                                                                                                                                                       LCD monitors. LED monitor's backlight uses
                                                                                                                                                                       less power and the screen gets brighter fast
                                                                                                                                                                       and  the  lighting  distribution  is  more  when
                                                                                                                                                                       compared to LCD.



                                                                                                                                         P
                                                                                                                                         PRINTERRINTER

                                                                                                                                       Printer gives the output of the computer programs on a paper. There are two types of
            Monochrome Monitor                                                                                                         printers namely Impact printer and Non-impact printer

            Monochrome monitor uses single colour and it resembles the black
            and white TV.  They are available in three different base colours namely

                              Softwhite    , Green Phosphor       , Amber

            The softwhite monochrome monitor was very commonly used. Now a
            days these monitors are not in use as the  advent of new technologies
            have made monitors more compact and easy to use.

            Colour Monitor
                                               Colour monitors are very similar to Colour TV, which can

                                               display different colours.  The colour monitors are capable                               IMP
                                                                                                                                         IMPACT PRINTERACT PRINTER
                                               of displaying different colours using the combination of
                                               the base colours Red, Green and Blue.                                                   In this type of printers the ribbon and the head comes in direct contact with the paper.

                                               The monitors are also available in different sizes such as                              Some examples of impact printers are :  Dot Matrix Printer             , Line Printer
                                               14", 17" and 21".  The display is seen in the monitor with                               D
                                                                                                                                        Dot Matrix Printerot Matrix Printer
                                               the help of Cathode Ray Tube (CRT). These are the oldest
                                               among all the available models these days. The best thing                               Dot  Matrix  Printer  can  print  characters  and  graphics  of

                                               in these monitors is that they are cheaper in price and                                 different sizes.  The output is printed as a combination of tiny
                                               their  drawback  is  their  weight,  size  and  they  consume                           dots. It can print at a speed of 300 characters per second (CPS)
                                               more power.                                                                             and more. The dot matrix printers comes in two standard sizes
                                                                                                                                       80 column and 132 column.
             10                                                                                                                                                                                                                          11]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                         ICT
 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
 C                                        COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                          C



            LCD MonitorD Monitor (Liquid Crystal Display)
 MONITOR    LC

 The monitor  is an output device used to display the result.  It is also called as Screen or   LCD monitor use ccfl back lights which contain Mercury. LCD
 Visual Display Unit (VDU).  The monitors are of two types  monitors  are  much  thinner,  lighter,  use  less  energy  and

           provide a greater graphics quality compared to CRT monitors.
            L
            LED MonitorED Monitor (Light Emitting Diode)




                                           LED monitor is basically the new version of
                                           LCD monitors. LED monitor's backlight uses
                                           less power and the screen gets brighter fast
                                           and  the  lighting  distribution  is  more  when
                                           compared to LCD.



            P
            PRINTERRINTER

           Printer gives the output of the computer programs on a paper. There are two types of
 Monochrome Monitor  printers namely Impact printer and Non-impact printer

 Monochrome monitor uses single colour and it resembles the black
 and white TV.  They are available in three different base colours namely

 Softwhite , Green Phosphor , Amber

 The softwhite monochrome monitor was very commonly used. Now a
 days these monitors are not in use as the  advent of new technologies
 have made monitors more compact and easy to use.

 Colour Monitor
 Colour monitors are very similar to Colour TV, which can

 display different colours.  The colour monitors are capable   IMP
            IMPACT PRINTERACT PRINTER
 of displaying different colours using the combination of
 the base colours Red, Green and Blue.  In this type of printers the ribbon and the head comes in direct contact with the paper.

 The monitors are also available in different sizes such as   Some examples of impact printers are :  Dot Matrix Printer , Line Printer
 14", 17" and 21".  The display is seen in the monitor with   D
            Dot Matrix Printerot Matrix Printer
 the help of Cathode Ray Tube (CRT). These are the oldest
 among all the available models these days. The best thing   Dot  Matrix  Printer  can  print  characters  and  graphics  of

 in these monitors is that they are cheaper in price and   different sizes.  The output is printed as a combination of tiny
 their  drawback  is  their  weight,  size  and  they  consume   dots. It can print at a speed of 300 characters per second (CPS)
 more power.  and more. The dot matrix printers comes in two standard sizes
           80 column and 132 column.
 10                                                                                                          11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                     ICT
                                                                                                                                                                       C
                                                                 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS                                                             COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                                                 C



             Lin
             Line Printere Printer                                                                                                     It has large storage capacity. The typical examples for secondary storage devices are
                                                                                                                                       Floppy disk, Hard disk and Compact disk.
            The  Line  Printer      can  print  300  to  3000  lines  per  minute.  The
                                                                                                                                         Floppy Diskloppy Disk
            quality of printing is not so good because the head comes in contact                                                         F
            with the paper for less time.                                                                                              It was developed by IBM Company. It is used to transfer data or software

             NON-IMPACT PRINTER                                                                                                        from one computer to other. A floppy disk is made up of mylar material
                                                                                                                                       with  magnetic  oxide  on  both  sides.  Initially  floppy  disks  were  8"  in
            These printers use a different technology to form images on paper and the head do not                                      diameter later it was replaced by 5¼ "and 3½ ".  Floppy disks are slower
            come in direct contact with the paper. They produce very less noise. Some examples of                                      to access and the storage capacity is also low when compared to other
            Non-Impact printers are: Inkjet printer            , Laser printer                                                         external storage devices. Now a days the floppy disks are not in use.

                                                                                                                                         H
             Ink
             Inkjet Printerjet Printer                                                                                                   Hard diskard disk    Hard disk is a metallic disk, coated with magnetic material, which is
            This printer has tiny nozzles (outlet), which sprays ink, forming                                                                                 permanently  fixed  inside  the  computer.  It  is  kept  in  airtight
                                                                                                                                                              environment that protects the disk from being damaged and also to
            images on the paper. This is achieved by using magnetized plates
            which direct the ink's path on to the paper in the desired pattern.                                                                               resist dust. The access (reading and writing) speed is more in the
                                                                                                                                                              case of Hard disk. They generally have large storage capacity, which
            The print quality is good in inkjet printers.
             Laser Printeraser Printer                                                                                                                        is measured in terms of gigabytes. Hard disk with a storage capacity
             L
                                                                                                                                                              of 4 TB (Terabyte) is also available. The capacity of the disk is likely
                                                                                                                                                              to increase in future.
                                                  The laser printer     works on the electrostatic technology.
                                                                                                                                         Compact disk (CD)ompact disk (CD)
                                                  It  is  similar  to  a  xerox  machine.  These  printers  can                          C
                                                  produce wide selection of characters and graphics and

                                                  print the same at a high speed. The laser printer can print                          The most proving technology for high external storage capacity is
                                                  up to 50 pages per minute.                                                           Compact Disk    , sometimes known as Laser disk or Optical disk. CD
             P                                                                                                                         is a small shiny circular plate made of polycarbonate and is about
             Plotterlotter
                                                                                                                                       12 cm in diameter along with a central hole.  The thickness of the
            Plotter  is  an  output  device  that  is  used  to  print  graphs  and
                                                                                                                                       CD is 12 mm.   Information on the disk is stored in the form of
            pictures. It draws picture on paper using multiple pens. The lines
                                                                                                                                       "pits" and "lands" using a beam of light.  As the disk rotates, the laser
            are not made up of dots but they are actually drawn providing
                                                                                                                                       head traces out a continuous signal to sense pits and lands.  This is converted into 1's
            infinite  resolution.  The  plotter  was  the  first  computer  output
                                                                                                                                       and 0's by the electronic interface and sent to the computer.
            device that could print graphs as well as accommodate full size
            engineering  and  architectural  drawings.  It  is  mainly  used  in                                                       CD's are of two types, Audio CD       and Video CD    .  In an Audio CD only sounds are digitized

            technical drawing and CAD (Computer Aided Design) applications.                                                            and stored whereas in a Video CD, the data can be in any form either text, still pictures or
             SP                                                                                                                        motion pictures with audio combination.   CD's can hold a gigabyte of data or more,
             SPEAKERSEAKERS
                                                                                                                                       which is twice the capacity of a floppy disk pack.
            Speakers  are  one  of  the  most  commonly  used  output  device  used  with  computers.
                                                                                                                                        Digital Versatile Disk (DVD)ital Versatile Disk (DVD)
            Speakers convert electrical signals into sound.                                                                             Dig
            SEC
            SECONDARY STORAGEONDARY STORAGE                                                                                            DVD is a storage device used to store large amount of data
                                                                                                                                       rather than compact disk. It was developed in the year 1995.
            Secondary storage devices stores data as per user's request. The main memory does not
                                                                                                                                       There are two types of DVD namely recordable and rewritable.
            store data permanently.  Due to this limitation, the secondary memory device has been
                                                                                                                                       DVDs are also available with different storage capacities.
            developed. These devices are also called as Auxiliary memory or External memory.
             12                                                                                                                                                                                                                          13]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[ICT
 C                                        C             ICT
 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                          COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS



 Line Printere Printer
 Lin       It has large storage capacity. The typical examples for secondary storage devices are
           Floppy disk, Hard disk and Compact disk.
 The  Line  Printer   can  print  300  to  3000  lines  per  minute.  The
            Floppy Diskloppy Disk
 quality of printing is not so good because the head comes in contact   F
 with the paper for less time.  It was developed by IBM Company. It is used to transfer data or software

 NON-IMPACT PRINTER  from one computer to other. A floppy disk is made up of mylar material
           with  magnetic  oxide  on  both  sides.  Initially  floppy  disks  were  8"  in
 These printers use a different technology to form images on paper and the head do not   diameter later it was replaced by 5¼ "and 3½ ".  Floppy disks are slower
 come in direct contact with the paper. They produce very less noise. Some examples of   to access and the storage capacity is also low when compared to other
 Non-Impact printers are: Inkjet printer , Laser printer  external storage devices. Now a days the floppy disks are not in use.

            Hard diskard disk
 Inkjet Printerjet Printer  H     Hard disk is a metallic disk, coated with magnetic material, which is
 Ink
 This printer has tiny nozzles (outlet), which sprays ink, forming   permanently  fixed  inside  the  computer.  It  is  kept  in  airtight
                                  environment that protects the disk from being damaged and also to
 images on the paper. This is achieved by using magnetized plates
 which direct the ink's path on to the paper in the desired pattern.   resist dust. The access (reading and writing) speed is more in the
                                  case of Hard disk. They generally have large storage capacity, which
 The print quality is good in inkjet printers.
 Laser Printeraser Printer
 L                                is measured in terms of gigabytes. Hard disk with a storage capacity
                                  of 4 TB (Terabyte) is also available. The capacity of the disk is likely
                                  to increase in future.
 The laser printer  works on the electrostatic technology.
            Compact disk (CD)ompact disk (CD)
 It  is  similar  to  a  xerox  machine.  These  printers  can   C
 produce wide selection of characters and graphics and

 print the same at a high speed. The laser printer can print   The most proving technology for high external storage capacity is
 up to 50 pages per minute.  Compact Disk , sometimes known as Laser disk or Optical disk. CD
 P
 Plotterlotter  is a small shiny circular plate made of polycarbonate and is about
           12 cm in diameter along with a central hole.  The thickness of the
 Plotter  is  an  output  device  that  is  used  to  print  graphs  and
           CD is 12 mm.   Information on the disk is stored in the form of
 pictures. It draws picture on paper using multiple pens. The lines
           "pits" and "lands" using a beam of light.  As the disk rotates, the laser
 are not made up of dots but they are actually drawn providing
           head traces out a continuous signal to sense pits and lands.  This is converted into 1's
 infinite  resolution.  The  plotter  was  the  first  computer  output
           and 0's by the electronic interface and sent to the computer.
 device that could print graphs as well as accommodate full size
 engineering  and  architectural  drawings.  It  is  mainly  used  in   CD's are of two types, Audio CD  and Video CD .  In an Audio CD only sounds are digitized

 technical drawing and CAD (Computer Aided Design) applications.  and stored whereas in a Video CD, the data can be in any form either text, still pictures or
 SPEAKERSEAKERS
 SP        motion pictures with audio combination.   CD's can hold a gigabyte of data or more,
           which is twice the capacity of a floppy disk pack.
 Speakers  are  one  of  the  most  commonly  used  output  device  used  with  computers.
 Speakers convert electrical signals into sound.  Digital Versatile Disk (DVD)Digital Versatile Disk (DVD)
 SEC
 SECONDARY STORAGEONDARY STORAGE  DVD is a storage device used to store large amount of data
           rather than compact disk. It was developed in the year 1995.
 Secondary storage devices stores data as per user's request. The main memory does not
           There are two types of DVD namely recordable and rewritable.
 store data permanently.  Due to this limitation, the secondary memory device has been
           DVDs are also available with different storage capacities.
 developed. These devices are also called as Auxiliary memory or External memory.
 12                                                                                                          13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[C
                                                                 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS





                                                                                                                                              FILL IN THE BLANKS
                                      DVD                                   CAPACITY
                    Single sided, single layer disk                  4.7 GB                                                            1. A set of instructions are fed into the computer through ________________                   unit.
                    Single sided, double layer disk                  8.5 GB - 8.7 GB
                    Double Sided, single layer disk                  9.4 GB                                                            2. __________________             is called brain of the computer.

                    Double Sided, double layer disk                  17.08 GB                                                          3. The result seen on the monitor is referred as __________________                 .

             Pen Driveen Drive
             P                                                                                                                         4. _________________           unit co-ordinates all other units of the computer.
            A Pen Drive     is a portable USB (Universal Serial Bus) flash memory                                                      5. ________________           are small memory of CPU which stores digital information.
            device for storing and transferring audio, video and data files from                                                       6. In ______________         , the program can be erased by using ultraviolet rays.

            a computer. It is used to store large amount of data and provides
                                                                                                                                       7. A floppy disk is made up of ___________________                 material.
            quick data transfer. It is small in size. It is also called as USB Flash
            drive  or  Thumb  drive.  It  is  available  with  different  memory                                                       8. In colour monitor, the display is seen with the help of __________________                  .
            capacities like 2GB, 4GB, 8GB, 16GB etc.
                                                                                                                                       9. The Webcam is the combination of ______________                  and _________________         .
            How to use the Pen drive
            It is very simple to use a pen drive. The user can insert one end of the drive which is                                    10. The laser printer works on the __________________                technology.

            equipped with a USB connector into the USB port on a desktop or laptop. Once the drive is                                  11. _______________         is a storage device used to store large amount of data rather
            active, files can be dragged and dropped or copied and pasted into the Pen drive.                                               than the compact disk.

             Memory Cardemory Card                                                                                                     12. A _________________           is a portable USB device.
             M
            A Memory Card        is used to store various types of electronic data. It is also referred as                             13. A memory card is used to store various types of _______________                  data.

            flash memory card; it is capable of storing a wide range of data files such as audio and
            video clips, images, and text documents.                                                                                   14. __________________           is the most commonly used input device.

            Memory card is used in computers, cell phones and in digital cameras. A card reader is                                     15. ________________________              draws picture on paper using multiple pens.
            essentially required for the memory card to be connected to the computer.
                                                                                                                                                TICK TRUE OR FALSE
                                                                                                                                        1. Control unit performs arithmetic and logical calculations.                    True          False


                                                                                                                                        2. RAM stands for Random Access Memory.                                          True          False

                                                                                                                                        3. 1024 KB makes one tera byte.                                                  True          False

                                                                                                                                        4. CD is otherwise known as Laser disk.                                          True          False

                                                                                                                                        5. Amber is the base colour of colour monitor.                                   True          False

                                                                                                                                        6. Scanner is an output device                                                   True          False
            It is available with different memory capacities like 2GB, 4GB, 8GB, 16GB etc. It also
            comes in different sizes.                                                                                                   7. Plotter is used to print graphs and pictures.                                 True          False




             14                                                                                                                                                                                                                          15]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[C
 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS





                  FILL IN THE BLANKS
 DVD  CAPACITY
 Single sided, single layer disk  4.7 GB  1. A set of instructions are fed into the computer through ________________  unit.
 Single sided, double layer disk  8.5 GB - 8.7 GB
 Double Sided, single layer disk  9.4 GB  2. __________________   is called brain of the computer.

 Double Sided, double layer disk  17.08 GB  3. The result seen on the monitor is referred as __________________ .

 Pen Driveen Drive
 P         4. _________________           unit co-ordinates all other units of the computer.
 A Pen Drive  is a portable USB (Universal Serial Bus) flash memory   5. ________________  are small memory of CPU which stores digital information.
 device for storing and transferring audio, video and data files from   6. In ______________ , the program can be erased by using ultraviolet rays.

 a computer. It is used to store large amount of data and provides
           7. A floppy disk is made up of ___________________                 material.
 quick data transfer. It is small in size. It is also called as USB Flash
 drive  or  Thumb  drive.  It  is  available  with  different  memory   8. In colour monitor, the display is seen with the help of __________________ .
 capacities like 2GB, 4GB, 8GB, 16GB etc.
           9. The Webcam is the combination of ______________                  and _________________         .
 How to use the Pen drive
 It is very simple to use a pen drive. The user can insert one end of the drive which is   10. The laser printer works on the __________________  technology.

 equipped with a USB connector into the USB port on a desktop or laptop. Once the drive is   11. _______________  is a storage device used to store large amount of data rather
 active, files can be dragged and dropped or copied and pasted into the Pen drive.   than the compact disk.

 Memory Cardemory Card  12. A _________________  is a portable USB device.
 M
 A Memory Card  is used to store various types of electronic data. It is also referred as   13. A memory card is used to store various types of _______________  data.

 flash memory card; it is capable of storing a wide range of data files such as audio and
 video clips, images, and text documents.    14. __________________  is the most commonly used input device.

 Memory card is used in computers, cell phones and in digital cameras. A card reader is   15. ________________________  draws picture on paper using multiple pens.
 essentially required for the memory card to be connected to the computer.
                    TICK TRUE OR FALSE
            1. Control unit performs arithmetic and logical calculations.                    True         False


            2. RAM stands for Random Access Memory.                                          True         False

            3. 1024 KB makes one tera byte.                                                  True         False

            4. CD is otherwise known as Laser disk.                                          True         False

            5. Amber is the base colour of colour monitor.                                   True         False

            6. Scanner is an output device                                                   True         False
 It is available with different memory capacities like 2GB, 4GB, 8GB, 16GB etc. It also
 comes in different sizes.  7. Plotter is used to print graphs and pictures.                 True         False




 14                                                                                                          15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                     ICT
                                                                 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                                                 C                                                                                                     COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                                                                                                                                                       C




             8. Joy stick is mainly used for playing games.                                    True         False                            ANSWER THE FOLLOWING
             9. Pen drive is also referred as flash memory card.                               True         False                      1. What is a computer? Name its main units.


             10. There are three types of DVD.                                                 True         False                      2. What are the three sub units of CPU?
                                                                                                                                       3. What is accumulator?
                  MATCH THE FOLLOWING                                                                                                  4. What is RAM? What are its types?


            1. Inkjet printer                          -      1 Nibble                                                                 5. What is a pendrive?

            2. Monochrome monitor                      -      uses tiny nozzles                                                        6. Write any two points on monochrome monitor and colour monitor.

            3. 4 Bits                                  -      online chatting                                                          7. Tabulate the chart of memory measurement.
                                                                                                                                       8. Write about the types of CD's.
            4. Web Cam                                 -      secondary storage device
                                                                                                                                       9. What are the two types of printer?
            5. Hard disk                               -      Green Phosphor
                                                                                                                                       10. What is Address?


                  CHOOSE THE CORRECT ANSWER                                                                                            11. Write a short note on DVD.
                                                                                                                                       12. What is touch screen?                                                                                     E
            1. The result in the printed form on a paper is referred as ________________                    .
                                                                                                                                       13. What is a scanner?
                                                                                     c)
               (  Softcopy                      (  Hardcopy                         (  Printcopy
                                                 b)
                a)
                                                                                                                                       14. Write a short note on LED monitor.                                                                        S
            2. The storage location in memory is identified by a unique number known as                                                15. What is the use of a memory card?
               _________________         .                                                                                                                                                                                                           I
                                                                                                                                             ANSWER THE FOLLOWING IN DETAIL
                                                                                     c)
                                                 b)
               (  Memory                        (  Location                         (  Address                                                                                                                                                       C
                a)
                                                                                                                                       1. How does a computer work? Explain with a neat diagram.
            3. ________________         stores the results of mathematical calculations temporarily.
                                                                                                                                       2. What is ROM? Explain its types.
                                                                                     c)
                                                 b)
                a)
               (  Accumulator                   (  Address                          (  Register                                                                                                                                                      R
                                                                                                                                       3. Write a note on Hard disk.
            4. ROM is a ________________             memory.                                                                           4. Discuss the various types of printers.
                                                 b)
               (  Non-volatile                  (  Volatile                         (  Static                                          5. Write a note on Floppy disk with a neat diagram.                                                           E
                a)
                                                                                     c)
            5. _____________        is an example of Non-Impact printer.                                                               6.  Discuss the various types of monitors.
                                                                                     c)
                                                 b)
                a)
               (  Line printer                  (  Dot Matrix printer               (  Laser printer                                                                                                                                                 X
                  EXPAND THE FOLLOWING                                                                                                                                                                                                               E

            1. CRT        2. EAROM       3. EPROM   4. CPS                   5. PROM              6. DVD

            7. USB        8. CAD                9. LCD        10. LED        11. DRAM             12. CMOS







             16                                                                                                                                                                                                                          17]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                         ICT
 COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
 C                                        COMPUTER FUNDAMENTALSOMPUTER FUNDAMENTALS
                                          C




 8. Joy stick is mainly used for playing games.  True  False  ANSWER THE FOLLOWING
 9. Pen drive is also referred as flash memory card.  True  False  1. What is a computer? Name its main units.


 10. There are three types of DVD.  True  False  2. What are the three sub units of CPU?
           3. What is accumulator?
 MATCH THE FOLLOWING  4. What is RAM? What are its types?


 1. Inkjet printer  -  1 Nibble  5. What is a pendrive?

 2. Monochrome monitor  -  uses tiny nozzles  6. Write any two points on monochrome monitor and colour monitor.

 3. 4 Bits  -  online chatting  7. Tabulate the chart of memory measurement.
           8. Write about the types of CD's.
 4. Web Cam  -  secondary storage device
           9. What are the two types of printer?
 5. Hard disk   -  Green Phosphor
           10. What is Address?


 CHOOSE THE CORRECT ANSWER  11. Write a short note on DVD.
           12. What is touch screen?                                                                                     E
 1. The result in the printed form on a paper is referred as ________________ .
           13. What is a scanner?
 c)
 (  Softcopy  (  Hardcopy  (  Printcopy
 b)
 a)
           14. Write a short note on LED monitor.                                                                        S
 2. The storage location in memory is identified by a unique number known as   15. What is the use of a memory card?
 _________________ .                                                                                                     I
                 ANSWER THE FOLLOWING IN DETAIL
 c)
 b)
 (  Memory  (  Location  (  Address                                                                                      C
 a)
           1. How does a computer work? Explain with a neat diagram.
 3. ________________  stores the results of mathematical calculations temporarily.
           2. What is ROM? Explain its types.
 c)
 b)
 a)
 (  Accumulator  (  Address  (  Register                                                                                 R
           3. Write a note on Hard disk.
 4. ROM is a ________________  memory.  4. Discuss the various types of printers.
 b)
 (  Non-volatile  (  Volatile  (  Static  5. Write a note on Floppy disk with a neat diagram.                            E
 a)
 c)
 5. _____________  is an example of Non-Impact printer.  6.  Discuss the various types of monitors.
 c)
 b)
 a)
 (  Line printer  (  Dot Matrix printer  (  Laser printer                                                                X
 EXPAND THE FOLLOWING                                                                                                    E

 1. CRT  2. EAROM       3. EPROM   4. CPS  5. PROM  6. DVD

 7. USB  8. CAD         9. LCD  10. LED  11. DRAM  12. CMOS







 16                                                                                                          17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                     ICT
                                                                                         CHAPTER 2CHAPTER 2                                                      INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                                                                                                                                                 I
                                                Introduction to                                                                        Touch



                                                                     Windows 7                                                         Touch is the new feature added to Windows 7. It is a new way of interacting with the

            Introduction                                                                                                               computer. This feature works only on those screens which are touch enabled.
                                                                                                                                       Desktop Gadgets
            As  we  need  energy  to  work,  a  car  needs  fuel  to  run,  similarly  computer  needs  an
            Operating System (OS) to make it work. Operating System is nothing but a program                                           Gadgets such as weather, clock, calendar, CPU meter etc., can be placed on desktop.

            which enables the computer to accept commands from the user to perform necessary                                           Aero Shake                                                        When many applications are open,
            actions.                                                                                                                   When many applications are open to minimize               Hint    to automatically minimize them, click

            An Operating System is thus defined as a collection of programs, which controls the                                        them in one shot, Aero shake can be used.                         and shake an open window.
            overall activities of the computer such as input, process, memory and storing of data.                                     Aero Snap
            Thus, it acts as an interface between the user and the computer. Some of the operating                                     Aero snap is used to resize and expand application windows quickly.
            systems are MS DOS, Windows, Unix and Linux.                                                                               Now let us discuss how files are manipulated in Windows 7 Operating System.

            We shall now discuss about Windows 7 Operating system.                                                                     FILES

             WINDOWS 7                                                                                                                 A file is a collection of information. It consists of text, pictures, numbers, sounds or
                                                                                                                                       combination of all. A file is identified by its name. For example “samsel.docx”. The
            Windows 7 is a computer operating system developed by Microsoft. It has a Graphical
                                                                                                                                       filename has three parts: Filename, a dot and the extension. Filename is the name given
            User Interface (GUI) that allows the user to interact with the items on the screen.
                                                                                                                                       to a file. Here the extension docx indicates that it is a document created using MS Word
                                                                                                                                       application.  The  dot  separates  the  filename  and  the  extension.  Some  of  the  file
                                                                                                                                       extensions are listed below:

                                                                                                                                                        EXTENSION                            MEANING
                                                                                                                                                            .txt            Extension of Notepad Application files
                                                                                                                                                            .bmp            Extension of Paint application files

                                                                                                                                                            .jpg            Extension of Picture files
                                                                                                                                                            .gif            Extension of Animated Picture files
                                                                                                                                                            .wav            Extension of Sound files


                                                                                                                                       FOLDERS

                                                                                                                                       When different files are grouped under one name then it is called a folder. A folder
                                                                                                                                       consists of files and sub folders.
                                                                                                                                       DRIVES

                                                                                                                                       The hard disk in the computer can be divided into two, three or more partitions and each
             FEATURES OF WINDOWS 7                                                                                                     partition is called a drive. A drive is a storage area in the hard disk where files, folders

                                                                                                                                       and application programs are stored.
            Some of the common features of Windows 7 are,
            Speed                                                                                                                      WINDOWS EXPLORER


            The time taken for booting the system is reduced when compared to other older versions.                                    Windows Explorer is a program, which manages the contents of the hard disk. It helps us
                                                                                                                                       to explore the files, folders and drives. To open Windows Explorer
             18                                                                                                                                                                                                                          19]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                         ICT
 CHAPTER 2CHAPTER 2                  INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                     I
 Introduction to   Touch



 Windows 7  Touch is the new feature added to Windows 7. It is a new way of interacting with the

 Introduction  computer. This feature works only on those screens which are touch enabled.
           Desktop Gadgets
 As  we  need  energy  to  work,  a  car  needs  fuel  to  run,  similarly  computer  needs  an
 Operating System (OS) to make it work. Operating System is nothing but a program   Gadgets such as weather, clock, calendar, CPU meter etc., can be placed on desktop.

 which enables the computer to accept commands from the user to perform necessary   Aero Shake  When many applications are open,
 actions.  When many applications are open to minimize               Hint   to automatically minimize them, click

 An Operating System is thus defined as a collection of programs, which controls the   them in one shot, Aero shake can be used.   and shake an open window.
 overall activities of the computer such as input, process, memory and storing of data.   Aero Snap
 Thus, it acts as an interface between the user and the computer. Some of the operating   Aero snap is used to resize and expand application windows quickly.
 systems are MS DOS, Windows, Unix and Linux.  Now let us discuss how files are manipulated in Windows 7 Operating System.

 We shall now discuss about Windows 7 Operating system.  FILES

 WINDOWS 7  A file is a collection of information. It consists of text, pictures, numbers, sounds or
           combination of all. A file is identified by its name. For example “samsel.docx”. The
 Windows 7 is a computer operating system developed by Microsoft. It has a Graphical
           filename has three parts: Filename, a dot and the extension. Filename is the name given
 User Interface (GUI) that allows the user to interact with the items on the screen.
           to a file. Here the extension docx indicates that it is a document created using MS Word
           application.  The  dot  separates  the  filename  and  the  extension.  Some  of  the  file
           extensions are listed below:

                            EXTENSION                            MEANING
                                .txt            Extension of Notepad Application files
                                .bmp            Extension of Paint application files

                                .jpg            Extension of Picture files
                                .gif            Extension of Animated Picture files
                                .wav            Extension of Sound files


           FOLDERS

           When different files are grouped under one name then it is called a folder. A folder
           consists of files and sub folders.
           DRIVES

           The hard disk in the computer can be divided into two, three or more partitions and each
 FEATURES OF WINDOWS 7  partition is called a drive. A drive is a storage area in the hard disk where files, folders

           and application programs are stored.
 Some of the common features of Windows 7 are,
 Speed     WINDOWS EXPLORER


 The time taken for booting the system is reduced when compared to other older versions.  Windows Explorer is a program, which manages the contents of the hard disk. It helps us
           to explore the files, folders and drives. To open Windows Explorer
 18                                                                                                          19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                            INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                                                                                                                                                 INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                                            I                                                                                                    I                   ICT


                                                                                                                                       OPEN A FILE / FOLDER
            i) Click on Start button and type Windows Explorer
                                                                                                                                       This option is used to view the contents of a file/folder. A file/folder can be opened in
               in the Search box.  (OR)                                                                                                three different ways.

            ii) Start  è    All Programs  è      Accessories  è                                                                        i)  Select the folder you want to open. Click on Open button from the Menu bar.
               Windows Explorer                                                                                                        ii)  Double click on the folder.

                                                                                                                                       iii)  Right click on the folder and select the option Open.
            The left part of Windows Explorer displays drives,
            folders and other hardware details and the right part                                                                      RENAME A FILE/FOLDER
            displays  files,  sub-folders  and  the  content  of  the
                                                                                                                                       This option is used to change the name of a file/folder. A folder can be renamed in two
            selected item on the left part.
                                                                                                                                       different ways.
             FILE MANAGEMENT                                                                                                           i)  Select the folder and click on Organize   Rename.
                                                                                                                                                                                        à
            Some of the basic operations that can be performed on files and folders are create, copy,                                  ii) Right click on the folder and select Rename.
            move and rename. We shall now discuss how to perform these operations in Windows                                           Then, type a new name and press Enter key.

            Explorer.                                                                                                                  COPY A FILE/FOLDER
            CREATION OF A FOLDER                                                                                                       This option is used to create a copy of file/folder in different location.

            To create a folder, open the drive in                                                                                      i)  Select  the  folder  and  click  on  Organize  à       Copy.  The  folder  gets  copied  on  the
            which  you  want  to  create  a  new                                                                                           clipboard.  Select  the  location  where  the  folder  has  to  get  copied.  Now  click  on

            folder. Creation of new folder can                                                                                             Organize  à
                                                                                                                                                          Paste. Thus the folder gets copied on to the selected location. (OR)
            be done in two different ways.                                                                                             ii)  Right click on the folder to be copied and then click on Copy. Now select the location.

            i)   Click on the New folder button,                                                                                           Right click on the empty area and select the option Paste.
                 which is present in the Menu                                                                                          MOVE A FILE/FOLDER
                 bar.
                                                                                                                                       This option is used to move a folder from one location to another. To move a folder
                 (OR)
                                                                                                                                       i)   Select the folder, click on Organize  à      Cut. Now select a different location where the
                                                                                                                                                                                                     Paste. The folder gets moved to the
                                                                                                                                           folder has to be moved then click on Organize  à
                                                                                                                                           selected location. (OR)

                                                                       ii) Right click and then select NEW                             ii)   Right click the folder and click on Cut. Then select the location. Right click on empty
                                                                           a  submenu  will  appear.  Then                                 area and select the option Paste.
                                                                           click on Folder.
                                                                                                                                       DELETE A FILE/FOLDER

                                                                                                                                       This option is used to delete a folder.

                                                                                                                                       i)  Select the folder and click on Organize à           Delete. (OR)
                                                                                  DO  Y U  KNOW?                                       ii) Right click on the folder and select the                   DO  Y U  KNOW?
                                                                                              O
                                                                                                                                                                                                                  O
                                                                                                                                           option Delete.
                                                                                    Unit Conversion, Date                                                                                            The keyboard shortcut for
                                                                                  Calculation, Lease Value                                                                                              Cut, Copy and Paste is
                                                                                Calculation can also be done                                                                                         Ctrl + X, Ctrl + C & Ctrl + V
             20                                                                 using Windows 7 Calculator.                                                                                                 respectively.                21]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[ICT
 INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                     INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
 I                                   I                  ICT


           OPEN A FILE / FOLDER
 i) Click on Start button and type Windows Explorer
           This option is used to view the contents of a file/folder. A file/folder can be opened in
 in the Search box.  (OR)  three different ways.

 ii) Start  è   All Programs  è  Accessories  è   i)  Select the folder you want to open. Click on Open button from the Menu bar.
 Windows Explorer  ii)  Double click on the folder.

           iii)  Right click on the folder and select the option Open.
 The left part of Windows Explorer displays drives,
 folders and other hardware details and the right part   RENAME A FILE/FOLDER
 displays  files,  sub-folders  and  the  content  of  the
           This option is used to change the name of a file/folder. A folder can be renamed in two
 selected item on the left part.
           different ways.
 FILE MANAGEMENT  i)  Select the folder and click on Organize   Rename.
                                                            à
 Some of the basic operations that can be performed on files and folders are create, copy,   ii) Right click on the folder and select Rename.
 move and rename. We shall now discuss how to perform these operations in Windows   Then, type a new name and press Enter key.

 Explorer.  COPY A FILE/FOLDER
 CREATION OF A FOLDER  This option is used to create a copy of file/folder in different location.

 To create a folder, open the drive in   i)  Select  the  folder  and  click  on  Organize  à   Copy.  The  folder  gets  copied  on  the
 which  you  want  to  create  a  new   clipboard.  Select  the  location  where  the  folder  has  to  get  copied.  Now  click  on

 folder. Creation of new folder can   Organize  à  Paste. Thus the folder gets copied on to the selected location. (OR)
 be done in two different ways.  ii)  Right click on the folder to be copied and then click on Copy. Now select the location.

 i)  Click on the New folder button,   Right click on the empty area and select the option Paste.
 which is present in the Menu   MOVE A FILE/FOLDER
 bar.
           This option is used to move a folder from one location to another. To move a folder
 (OR)
           i)   Select the folder, click on Organize  à      Cut. Now select a different location where the
                                                                         Paste. The folder gets moved to the
               folder has to be moved then click on Organize  à
               selected location. (OR)

 ii) Right click and then select NEW   ii)   Right click the folder and click on Cut. Then select the location. Right click on empty
 a  submenu  will  appear.  Then   area and select the option Paste.
 click on Folder.
           DELETE A FILE/FOLDER

           This option is used to delete a folder.

           i)  Select the folder and click on Organize à           Delete. (OR)
 DO  Y U  KNOW?  ii) Right click on the folder and select the             DO  Y U  KNOW?
 O
                                                                                      O
               option Delete.
 Unit Conversion, Date                                                   The keyboard shortcut for
 Calculation, Lease Value                                                  Cut, Copy and Paste is
 Calculation can also be done                                            Ctrl + X, Ctrl + C & Ctrl + V
 20  using Windows 7 Calculator.                                                respectively.                21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                     ICT
                                                            I                                                                                                    INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                                            INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                                                                                                                                                 I




             VIEWING FILES AND FOLDERS                                                                                                 MEDIUM ICONS


            Change your view         button helps to view the files and folders in different ways. This                                                                                          It gives a good idea of the content
            option is available in the upper right corner of the window. The More options button will                                                                                            but the icon size is smaller than the
            display a list of views as follows                                                                                                                                                   Large Icons.
                     1. Extra large icons


                     2. Large icons


                     3. Medium icons

                     4. Small icons


                     5. List

                     6. Details                                                                                                         SMALL ICONS

                                                                                                                                       Small Icons view is much smaller than
                     7. Tiles
                                                                                                                                       the  Medium  Icons.  Here  the  folders

                     8. Content                                                                                                        and files are displayed as icons with
                                                                                                                                       their names in the right side. If the
            The files/folders can also be viewed by Right clicking at any blank area and selecting the
                                                                                                                                       file/folder name is big, it displays only
            option view.                                                                                                               the first part of it.



             EXTRA LARGE ICONS & LARGE ICONS

            Extra Large Icons gives the biggest view of the folders. Large Icons also gives a bigger
            view of the folders but the view is smaller when compared to Extra Large Icons.
                                                                                                                                       LIST



                                                                                                                                                                                                 In this view, the folders are displayed
                                                                                                                                                                                                 one below the other followed by files.















                          Extra large icons                                         Large icons



             22                                                                                                                                                                                                                          23]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                         ICT
 I                                   INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
 INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                     I




 VIEWING FILES AND FOLDERS  MEDIUM ICONS


 Change your view         button helps to view the files and folders in different ways. This   It gives a good idea of the content
 option is available in the upper right corner of the window. The More options button will   but the icon size is smaller than the
 display a list of views as follows                                  Large Icons.
 1. Extra large icons


 2. Large icons


 3. Medium icons

 4. Small icons


 5. List

 6. Details   SMALL ICONS

           Small Icons view is much smaller than
 7. Tiles
           the  Medium  Icons.  Here  the  folders

 8. Content  and files are displayed as icons with
           their names in the right side. If the
 The files/folders can also be viewed by Right clicking at any blank area and selecting the
           file/folder name is big, it displays only
 option view.  the first part of it.



 EXTRA LARGE ICONS & LARGE ICONS

 Extra Large Icons gives the biggest view of the folders. Large Icons also gives a bigger
 view of the folders but the view is smaller when compared to Extra Large Icons.
           LIST



                                                                     In this view, the folders are displayed
                                                                     one below the other followed by files.















 Extra large icons  Large icons



 22                                                                                                          23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                                            I




            DETAILS                                                   Details view is similar to list view but it                            FILL IN THE BLANKS

                                                                      gives more information. In this view                             1. _________________           acts as an interface between the user and computer.
                                                                      also, the folder names are displayed
                                                                      first one below the other preceeded by                           2. _______________          feature of Windows7 is used to resize the application

                                                                      small icons, then followed by files.                                  windows quickly.
                                                                      For Folders  : It displays the date and                          3. A file is a collection of _________________             .
                                                                      the  time  it  was  created  or  last
                                                                      modified.                                                        4. Sound files are stored with the extension _________________                   .
                                                                      For Files : It displays the file size, the                       5. The partitions in the hard disk are called _________________                  .

                                                                      application name along with the date
                                                                                                                                       6. GUI stands for_________________               .
                                                                      and  time  it  was  created  or  last
                                                                      modified.                                                        7. _________________           consists of files and sub-folders.


            TILES                                                                                                                      8. _________________           option is used to change the name of the folder.

            In tiles view, the files and folders are                                                                                   9. The Keyboard shortcut for cut is _________________                  .
            displayed  as  icons  with  their                                                                                          10. _________________         button helps to view the files and folders in different ways.
            respective  names  on  the  right  side.                                                                                                                                                                                                   E
            For  Files  it  also  displays  the                                                                                              TICK TRUE OR FALSE

            application  name  and  the  file  size
            too.  Here  it  displays  the  complete                                                                                    1. In Windows 7, Gadgets such as weather, clock etc., cannot                       True          False          S
            file/folder name.                                                                                                             be placed on Desktop.
                                                                                                                                       2. A filename has three parts.                                                     True          False          I


                                                                                                                                       3. The Keyboard shortcut for paste in Ctrl + P.                                    True          False          C

            CONTENT                                                                                                                    4. Cut Option is used to move a folder.                                            True          False


                                                                                                                                       5. .wav is the extension of Paint application files.                               True          False          R
                                                                      Content  view  displays  the  folders
                                                                      and  files  row  wise  with  detailed                                  MATCH THE FOLLOWING

                                                                      information.                                                                                                                                                                     E
                                                                                                                                       1. Unix                                    -      .jpg


                                                                                                                                       2. Picture files                           -      content of the hard disk                                      X

                                                                                                                                       3. Notepad extension                       -      .gif

                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       E
                                                                                                                                       4. Windows Explorer                        -      .txt

                                                                                                                                       5. Animated picture files                  -      Operating System


             24                                                                                                                                                                                                                          25]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
 I




 DETAILS  Details view is similar to list view but it   FILL IN THE BLANKS

 gives more information. In this view   1. _________________  acts as an interface between the user and computer.
 also, the folder names are displayed
 first one below the other preceeded by   2. _______________  feature of Windows7 is used to resize the application

 small icons, then followed by files.  windows quickly.
 For Folders : It displays the date and   3. A file is a collection of _________________ .
 the  time  it  was  created  or  last
 modified.  4. Sound files are stored with the extension _________________                  .
 For Files : It displays the file size, the   5. The partitions in the hard disk are called _________________ .

 application name along with the date
           6. GUI stands for_________________              .
 and  time  it  was  created  or  last
 modified.  7. _________________          consists of files and sub-folders.


 TILES     8. _________________           option is used to change the name of the folder.

 In tiles view, the files and folders are   9. The Keyboard shortcut for cut is _________________ .
 displayed  as  icons  with  their   10. _________________ button helps to view the files and folders in different ways.
 respective  names  on  the  right  side.                                                                                 E
 For  Files  it  also  displays  the   TICK TRUE OR FALSE

 application  name  and  the  file  size
 too.  Here  it  displays  the  complete   1. In Windows 7, Gadgets such as weather, clock etc., cannot   True  False     S
 file/folder name.  be placed on Desktop.
           2. A filename has three parts.                                                     True         False          I


           3. The Keyboard shortcut for paste in Ctrl + P.                                    True         False          C

 CONTENT   4. Cut Option is used to move a folder.                                            True         False


           5. .wav is the extension of Paint application files.                               True         False          R
 Content  view  displays  the  folders
 and  files  row  wise  with  detailed   MATCH THE FOLLOWING

 information.                                                                                                             E
           1. Unix                                    -      .jpg


           2. Picture files                           -      content of the hard disk                                     X

           3. Notepad extension                       -      .gif

                                                                                                                          E
           4. Windows Explorer                        -      .txt

           5. Animated picture files                  -      Operating System


 24                                                                                                          25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                 INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                                            I                                                                                                    I                   ICT
                                                            INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7




                   CHOOSE THE CORRECT ANSWER                                                                                                   ANSWER THE FOLLOWING IN DETAIL
                                                                                                                                        1. Explain Windows Explorer and its parts.
            1. In Windows 7, the time taken for booting the System is ________________                       when                       2. What are the operations involved in File Management? Explain any three.

               compared to other older versions.
                                                                                                                                        3. Explain the different View options.
               a) Increased                     b)  Reduced                         c)  Same

            2. ___________       separates filename and the extension.                                                                                    try
                                                                                                                                                          in your
               a) Semi-colon                    b)  Dot                            c)  Comma                                                                     lab

            3. Sound files are saved with the extension _____________                .
                                                                                                                                          1.   Create a file containing information about
               a) .gif                          b)  .sou                           c)  .wav                                                    "Role of Computer in today's life" in Notepad.

            4. To ____________        a folder select the folder, Click on organize   cut.
                                                                                             à
                                                                                                                                                    1 Save the file as "Computer" in D drive.
               a) Move                          b)  Copy                            c)  Paste                                                       1 Create a folder named "PC" in D drive.

            5. The Keyboard shortcut for copy is ____________               .                                             E                         1 Copy the file "Computer" to "PC" folder.                                                   E


               a) Ctrl + X                      b)  Ctrl + C                        c)  Ctrl + V
                                                                                                                          S              2. Create the following Folder and Sub-folders in F drive:

                   ANSWER THE FOLLOWING                                                                                                                                                                                                          S

                                                                                                                          I
            1. What is an Operating System?                                                                                                                                                                                                      I


            2. Name any four File extensions.                                                                             C                                                                                                                      C

            3. What is a File?  Explain its parts.                                                                        R

            4. What is Folder?                                                                                                                                                                                                                   R

                                                                                                                          E
            5. What is Drive?

            6. How will you create a Folder?                                                                                                                                                                                                     E

            7. Name any four Views.                                                                                       X


            8. Give some examples of Operating System.                                                                                                   1    Make a copy of the above folders in D drive.                                       X

            9. How will you delete a file or folder?                                                                      E                              1    Rename the folder "Animals" to "Creatures".
                                                                                                                                                         1    Move the folder "Wild animals" to E drive.
            10. What are the features of Windows7 Operating System?                                                                                                                                                                              E
                                                                                                                                                         1    Rename the folder "Cat" to "Cow".

                                                                                                                                                         1    Delete the folder "Domestic animals".



             26                                                                                                                                                                                                                          27]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[ICT
                                     INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
 I                                   I                  ICT
 INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7




 CHOOSE THE CORRECT ANSWER  ANSWER THE FOLLOWING IN DETAIL
            1. Explain Windows Explorer and its parts.
 1. In Windows 7, the time taken for booting the System is ________________  when   2. What are the operations involved in File Management? Explain any three.

 compared to other older versions.
            3. Explain the different View options.
 a) Increased     b)  Reduced  c)  Same

 2. ___________  separates filename and the extension.  try
                              in your
 a) Semi-colon      b)  Dot                c)  Comma  lab

 3. Sound files are saved with the extension _____________ .
             1.    Create a file containing information about
 a) .gif     b)  .sou                c)  .wav  "Role of Computer in today's life" in Notepad.

 4. To ____________  a folder select the folder, Click on organize   cut.
 à
                        1 Save the file as "Computer" in D drive.
 a) Move      b)  Copy                c)  Paste  1 Create a folder named "PC" in D drive.

 5. The Keyboard shortcut for copy is ____________ .  E  1 Copy the file "Computer" to "PC" folder.                  E


 a) Ctrl + X      b)  Ctrl + C                c)  Ctrl + V
 S           2. Create the following Folder and Sub-folders in F drive:

 ANSWER THE FOLLOWING                                                                                                S

 I
 1. What is an Operating System?                                                                                     I


 2. Name any four File extensions.  C                                                                                C

 3. What is a File?  Explain its parts.  R

 4. What is Folder?                                                                                                  R

 E
 5. What is Drive?

 6. How will you create a Folder?                                                                                    E

 7. Name any four Views.  X


 8. Give some examples of Operating System.  1  Make a copy of the above folders in D drive.                         X

 9. How will you delete a file or folder?  E  1  Rename the folder "Animals" to "Creatures".
                             1    Move the folder "Wild animals" to E drive.
 10. What are the features of Windows7 Operating System?                                                             E
                             1    Rename the folder "Cat" to "Cow".

                             1    Delete the folder "Domestic animals".



 26                                                                                                          27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                                      CHAPTER 3APTER 3
                                                                                                                                                                                                      CH
                                                            INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
                                                            I                                                                                                                        ICT
                                                                                                                                                                           MS Word 2007


                        try
                        in your                                                                                                        Introduction
                             lab                                                                                                       In earlier days to print letters, prepare statements or documents a manual typewriter


             3. Create the folder and sub-folders in F drive as shown below:                                                           was used which was later replaced by electronic typewriter machine. The invention of

                                                                                                                                       computers quickly replaced most of manual documentation and almost the typewriters
                                                                                                                                       are extinct in most workplaces.

                                                                                                                                        WORD PROCESSORS

                                                                                                                                       As  computers  are  fast  replacing  most  of  the  manual  documentation  work,  software
                                                                                                                                       technically called "Word Processors" are introduced to process text. Word Processors are
                                                                                                                                       application software that are used for creating, editing, sorting and printing all kinds of
                                                                                                                                       documents. Some examples of word processors are Microsoft Word 2003, MS Word 2007,
                                                                                                                                       MS Word 2010, Adobe Acrobat and Open office.


                                                                                                                 E                     Word processors are applied in the fields of journalism, E-Publishing and DTP (Desk Top
                                                                                                                                       Publishing). Thus Word processing is integral for the preparation and presentation of

                                                                                                                                       documents.
                                                                                                                 S                     MS Word 2007 was developed by Microsoft Corporation. It has gained its popularity due
                                                                                                                                        FEATURES OF MS WORD 2007


                                                                                                                                       to its advanced features. Some of them are
                                                                                                                 I
                1    Make a copy of "Parrot" in Flightless.                                                                            1.  It comes with a gallery of building blocks, which can drop into a document to add
                                                                                                                                            elements like headers, footers, cover pages, slide bars etc.
                1    Move the folder "Flightless" into "Flight".                                                 C                     2.  It adds a great multilane view that makes comparing different versions of the same
                     (Use Mouse not Menu option)                                                                                            document easy.


                1    Rename the folder "Parrot" to "Crow" in Flight and                                          R                     3.  The new Contextual spelling checker is a wonderful feature.
                                                                                                                                        G
                                                                                                                                        GETTING INTO MS WORD 2007ETTING INTO MS WORD 2007
                     delete the same.                                                                            E                     One of the common ways to get into


                1    Create one more folder in "Flight" and name it as                                                                 MS Word 2007 is using the Start
                     "Dove".                                                                                     X                     button   .                Microsoft Office
                                                                                                                                                  Programs ð
                                                                                                                                       Start ð
                1    Move the "Birds" folder from F drive to desktop.                                                                  ð   Microsoft Office Word 2007.
                                                                                                                 E

              4. Open F drive view all the files and folders using

                  different view options and note down the difference.




             28                                                                                                                                                                                                                          29]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                         CHAPTER 3APTER 3
                                                                         CH
 INTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7NTRODUCTION TO WINDOWS 7
 I                                                      ICT
                                               MS Word 2007


 try
 in your    Introduction
 lab       In earlier days to print letters, prepare statements or documents a manual typewriter


 3. Create the folder and sub-folders in F drive as shown below:  was used which was later replaced by electronic typewriter machine. The invention of

           computers quickly replaced most of manual documentation and almost the typewriters
           are extinct in most workplaces.

           WORD PROCESSORS

           As  computers  are  fast  replacing  most  of  the  manual  documentation  work,  software
           technically called "Word Processors" are introduced to process text. Word Processors are
           application software that are used for creating, editing, sorting and printing all kinds of
           documents. Some examples of word processors are Microsoft Word 2003, MS Word 2007,
           MS Word 2010, Adobe Acrobat and Open office.


 E         Word processors are applied in the fields of journalism, E-Publishing and DTP (Desk Top
           Publishing). Thus Word processing is integral for the preparation and presentation of

           documents.
 S         MS Word 2007 was developed by Microsoft Corporation. It has gained its popularity due
           FEATURES OF MS WORD 2007


           to its advanced features. Some of them are
 I
 1  Make a copy of "Parrot" in Flightless.  1.  It comes with a gallery of building blocks, which can drop into a document to add
                elements like headers, footers, cover pages, slide bars etc.
 1  Move the folder "Flightless" into "Flight".  C  2.  It adds a great multilane view that makes comparing different versions of the same
 (Use Mouse not Menu option)  document easy.


 1  Rename the folder "Parrot" to "Crow" in Flight and   R  3.  The new Contextual spelling checker is a wonderful feature.
           G
           GETTING INTO MS WORD 2007ETTING INTO MS WORD 2007
 delete the same.  E  One of the common ways to get into


 1  Create one more folder in "Flight" and name it as   MS Word 2007 is using the Start
 "Dove".  X  button .                Microsoft Office
                     Programs ð
           Start ð
 1  Move the "Birds" folder from F drive to desktop.  ð  Microsoft Office Word 2007.
 E

 4. Open F drive view all the files and folders using

     different view options and note down the difference.




 28                                                                                                          29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                              MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                                        MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                                        M                                                                                            ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                              M

            COMPONENTS OF MS WORD 2007 WINDOW                                                                                          Scroll bars

            The Microsoft Office button                                                                                                Scroll bars are used to scroll across the window (up, down, left and right).There are two

            This button is found at the top left part of the MS Word 2007 window. This button helps us                                 types of scroll bars namely horizontal and vertical. A horizontal scroll bar is used to scroll

            to perform many functions. Using this button we can create a new document, open an                                         from left to right and vice versa and the vertical scroll bar is used for up and down
            existing document, save a document, print, send a document through (E-mail or Fax) or                                      movement and vice versa.
            close the current document.
                                                                                                                                       Rulers
            Quick Access Toolbar
                                                                                                                                       Rulers control the margins of the page. They appear on the top and left side of the
            By default this toolbar appears next to the MS Office Button. The Quick access toolbar                                     work area.
            helps us to access the frequently used commands. In other words, it is a shortcut to

            frequently used commands. By default only three buttons appear on this tool bar Save,                                       CREATING A NEW DOCUMENT
            Undo and Redo. The Save button is to save the document. The Undo button is to roll back                                    To  create  a  new  document  in  MS  Word
            an action and Redo is to apply the same action again.                                                                      2007, the following methods are used.

            Note: The keyboard short cuts for Save is Ctrl + S, Undo and Redo are Ctrl + Z and                                         Method  1   :  Click  on  the  Microsoft  office
            Ctrl + Y respectively.                                                                                                     button and then click on New option. A list

            We can also add other commands to this tool bar by right clicking on any command in the                                    of choices are displayed about the type of
            MS Office button or in the Ribbon and click on 'Add to Quick Access toolbar'. By doing this                                document  to  be  created.  Click  on  the
            a shortcut will be added to the Quick Access toolbar.                                                                      option  Blank  document  to  start  a  new
                                                                                                                                       document.
            Ribbon
                                                                                                                                       Method 2   : Using the keyboard shortcut Ctrl
            The Ribbon is a collection of tabs in a panel at the top portion of the document. It is
            designed to help us to find the commands quickly to complete a task. The commands are                                      + N, a new blank document can be created.
            organised in groups, which are collected together under tabs. The ribbon has seven tabs                                     ENTERING TEXT IN A NEW DOCUMENT
            as shown in the picture below:
                                                                                                                                       Once the blank document is created, it is ready for typing text. The text will appear on the
                                                                                                                                       work area where the blinking cursor is located. As the text is typed the cursor moves
                                                                                                                                       towards the right of the screen.







                                                          Ribbon

            Each tab contains many features for carrying out related type of activities. The ribbon
            can be minimized to make more space on the screen.

            Note: The keyboard short cut key for minimizing / maximizing the ribbon is Ctrl+ F1.
            Work Area

            It is a blank area where the text can be keyed in. It has a blinking vertical line called

            cursor that indicates where the text will appear.                                                                                                             Entering text in a document
             30                                                                                                                                                                                                                          31]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                  MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
 MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
 M                                                      ICT
                                                                  M

 COMPONENTS OF MS WORD 2007 WINDOW  Scroll bars

 The Microsoft Office button  Scroll bars are used to scroll across the window (up, down, left and right).There are two

 This button is found at the top left part of the MS Word 2007 window. This button helps us   types of scroll bars namely horizontal and vertical. A horizontal scroll bar is used to scroll

 to perform many functions. Using this button we can create a new document, open an   from left to right and vice versa and the vertical scroll bar is used for up and down
 existing document, save a document, print, send a document through (E-mail or Fax) or   movement and vice versa.
 close the current document.
           Rulers
 Quick Access Toolbar
           Rulers control the margins of the page. They appear on the top and left side of the
 By default this toolbar appears next to the MS Office Button. The Quick access toolbar   work area.
 helps us to access the frequently used commands. In other words, it is a shortcut to

 frequently used commands. By default only three buttons appear on this tool bar Save,   CREATING A NEW DOCUMENT
 Undo and Redo. The Save button is to save the document. The Undo button is to roll back   To  create  a  new  document  in  MS  Word
 an action and Redo is to apply the same action again.  2007, the following methods are used.

 Note: The keyboard short cuts for Save is Ctrl + S, Undo and Redo are Ctrl + Z and   Method  1 :  Click  on  the  Microsoft  office
 Ctrl + Y respectively.  button and then click on New option. A list

 We can also add other commands to this tool bar by right clicking on any command in the   of choices are displayed about the type of
 MS Office button or in the Ribbon and click on 'Add to Quick Access toolbar'. By doing this   document  to  be  created.  Click  on  the
 a shortcut will be added to the Quick Access toolbar.  option  Blank  document  to  start  a  new
           document.
 Ribbon
           Method 2   : Using the keyboard shortcut Ctrl
 The Ribbon is a collection of tabs in a panel at the top portion of the document. It is
 designed to help us to find the commands quickly to complete a task. The commands are   + N, a new blank document can be created.
 organised in groups, which are collected together under tabs. The ribbon has seven tabs   ENTERING TEXT IN A NEW DOCUMENT
 as shown in the picture below:
           Once the blank document is created, it is ready for typing text. The text will appear on the
           work area where the blinking cursor is located. As the text is typed the cursor moves
           towards the right of the screen.







 Ribbon

 Each tab contains many features for carrying out related type of activities. The ribbon
 can be minimized to make more space on the screen.

 Note: The keyboard short cut key for minimizing / maximizing the ribbon is Ctrl+ F1.
 Work Area

 It is a blank area where the text can be keyed in. It has a blinking vertical line called

 cursor that indicates where the text will appear.  Entering text in a document
 30                                                                                                          31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                              MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                                                                                                                                              M
                                                                                        M
                                                                                        MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007                                                                      ICT

            SAVING A DOCUMENT

            The Save option helps us to store the document in the computer for future purpose. To                                       CLOSING A DOCUMENT

            save a document click on the Microsoft office button and click Save option, the Save As                                    A document must be closed after using it. To close the current document click the option
            dialog box appears as shown below. Now type a file name and click on Save button.                                          Close. This is the last option in MS Office button. If the file contains any unsaved changes
                                                                                                                                       MS Word 2007 prompts to save the changes by displaying the confirmation dialogue box
                                                                                                                                       as shown.


                                                                                                                                                                                                                                Hint

                                                                                                                                                                                                                          Use Ctrl + W or
                                                                                                                                                                                                                              Ctrl + F4
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             to close the
                                                                                                                                                                                                                         current document.





                                                     Save a document
            Note: The keyboard shortcut for saving a document is Ctrl+S.
                                                                                                                                       We can also close MS Word 2007 by clicking on
            SAVE AS OPTION                                                                                                             the close button     . This is found at the top


            The Save As option is used to save the document in a different location or with a different                                right corner of the document. If the file has
            name. To use this option click on the Microsoft office button and then select the option                                   been  saved  before  and  there  are  no  new
            Save As. Now type a new file name to save the document with a different name.                                              changes, MS Word simply closes the file. The
                                                                                                                                       keyboard shortcut for closing a document is
            Note: The keyboard shortcut for Save As option is F12 (Function key).
                                                                                                                                       Ctrl + F4.
                            Difference between Save                  and Save As         option
                                                                                                                                        OPENING AN EXISTING DOCUMENT



                                    SAVE                                   SAVE AS                                                                                                               The  Open  option  is  used  to  open  an
                                                                                                                                                                                                 existing document. To open a document
                       To save a document for the first         To make a copy of the document                                                                                                   click  on  MS  Office  button  and  select
                       time the save option used.               the Save As option is used.                                                                                                      the option Open. The Open dialog box
                                                                                                                                                                                                 appears as shown, displaying a list of
                       Each time when this option is            Each time when this option is                                                                                                    files. You can choose the document by
                       used the document is simply              used the document is saved with                                                                                                  clicking on the filename and click Open
                       saved with the same name.                a different name or location or                                                                                                  button  or  if  you  have  used  the  file
                                                                both.
                                                                                                                                                                                                 recently you can choose the file from
                       The keyboard shortcut for Save           The keyboard shortcut for Save As
                       option is Ctrl + S.                      option is F12.                                                                                                                   recent document section.



                                                                                                                                       Note: The keyboard shortcut for opening a document is Ctrl + O.

             32                                                                                                                                                                                                                          33]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                  MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                  M
 M
 MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007                                ICT

 SAVING A DOCUMENT

 The Save option helps us to store the document in the computer for future purpose. To   CLOSING A DOCUMENT

 save a document click on the Microsoft office button and click Save option, the Save As    A document must be closed after using it. To close the current document click the option
 dialog box appears as shown below. Now type a file name and click on Save button.  Close. This is the last option in MS Office button. If the file contains any unsaved changes
           MS Word 2007 prompts to save the changes by displaying the confirmation dialogue box
           as shown.


                                                                                                    Hint

                                                                                              Use Ctrl + W or
                                                                                                  Ctrl + F4
                                                                                                 to close the
                                                                                             current document.





 Save a document
 Note: The keyboard shortcut for saving a document is Ctrl+S.
           We can also close MS Word 2007 by clicking on
 SAVE AS OPTION  the close button     . This is found at the top


 The Save As option is used to save the document in a different location or with a different   right corner of the document. If the file has
 name. To use this option click on the Microsoft office button and then select the option   been  saved  before  and  there  are  no  new
 Save As. Now type a new file name to save the document with a different name.  changes, MS Word simply closes the file. The
           keyboard shortcut for closing a document is
 Note: The keyboard shortcut for Save As option is F12 (Function key).
           Ctrl + F4.
 Difference between Save  and Save As  option
           OPENING AN EXISTING DOCUMENT



 SAVE  SAVE AS                                                       The  Open  option  is  used  to  open  an
                                                                     existing document. To open a document
 To save a document for the first   To make a copy of the document   click  on  MS  Office  button  and  select
 time the save option used.  the Save As option is used.             the option Open. The Open dialog box
                                                                     appears as shown, displaying a list of
 Each time when this option is  Each time when this option is        files. You can choose the document by
 used the document is simply  used the document is saved with        clicking on the filename and click Open
 saved with the same name.  a different name or location or          button  or  if  you  have  used  the  file
 both.
                                                                     recently you can choose the file from
 The keyboard shortcut for Save  The keyboard shortcut for Save As
 option is Ctrl + S.  option is F12.                                 recent document section.



           Note: The keyboard shortcut for opening a document is Ctrl + O.

 32                                                                                                          33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[M
                                                                                        MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007                                                                               MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                                        M


            EXITING MS WORD 2007                                                                                                        TEXT INSERTION

            To close MS Word 2007 application click on MS Office button and select the option Exit                                     To insert text in a document we can move the cursor to the desired location where the text

            Word. This option is found in the lower right corner of MS Office button. We can also Exit                                 is to be inserted and simply start typing. We can also insert text in a document by other
            by double clicking on MS Office button. The keyboard shortcut is ALT+F4.                                                   methods using cut, copy and paste options. Now let us discuss the other methods.
            TEXT SELECTION                                                                                                              CUT OPTION

            To work or edit any text it is necessary to select a particular text that includes a word, line
                                                                                                                                       This option is used to cut a particular portion of the text and temporarily place it on the
            or a paragraph. The text can be selected in two different ways, namely
                                                                                                                                       clipboard. In other words, this option is used to move a portion of the text from one part of
                                         •      Using keyboard                                                                         the document to the other position in the same document or can be placed in some other

                                         •      Using Mouse                                                                            document too. To perform the cut option follow the steps given below.
            SELECTING TEXT WITH KEYBOARD                                                                                               Step 1  :  Select the text that you wish to cut (using the Mouse or Shift + arrow key)

            This  way  of  selection  is  done  when  a  particular  word,  line  or  paragraph  has  to  be                           Step 2  :  Right click and select the option Cut. Now the highlighted text is removed from
            selected. Keyboard selection is carried out by pressing the Shift key along with the                                                  the current position and placed on the clipboard, which is a temporary storage
            appropriate arrow keys.                                                                                                                 area.

            SELECTING TEXT WITH MOUSE                                                                                                  Note: The keyboard shortcut for performing the cut action is Ctrl + X              . The Cut option is

            The mouse selection can be done by placing the cursor at the beginning of the text,                                        always followed by the Paste option.
            holding the left mouse button and dragging across the text that is to be selected. Once                                     PASTE OPTION
            the desired text is selected, it will be highlighted. The text can be deselected by clicking
                                                                                                                                       This option is used to insert the contents of the clipboard (contains text cut/copied) at the
            the mouse outside the selected area.
                                                                                                                                       cursor position where the desired text is required. To perform the paste option follow the
                                                                                                                                       steps given below.

                                                                                                                                       Step 1  :  Place the cursor at the position, where you want the text to be inserted.

                                                                                                                                       Step 2  : Right click on the mouse and select the option Paste. Now the selected text is
                                                                                                                                                  pasted. The keyboard shortcut for the Paste option is Ctrl + V         .
                                                                                                                                        COPY OPTION

                                                                                                                                       This option is used to make a copy of a part of the text or the whole text in the same
                                                                                                                                       document or in a different document at the cursor position. To perform the copy option
                                                                                                                                       follow the steps given below.

                                                                                                                                       Step 1  :  Select the text which you want to copy.

                                                                                                                                       Step 2  :  Right  click  on  the  mouse  and  select  the  option  copy.  Now  a  copy  of  the
                                                                                                                                                  highlighted text is placed on the clipboard, but the original text remains in the
            Note:
                                                                                                                                                  same position. The Copy option is also followed by the Paste option.
            •   To select a word double-click within the word.
                                                                                                                                       Place the cursor at the position where you want a copy of the text to be inserted (either in
            •   To select a paragraph triple-click within the paragraph.                                                               the same document or open another document). Then right click on the mouse and select

            •   To select the entire document click on the select button located in the right corner                                   the option Paste. This action will paste a copy of the text at the cursor position.
                of the Home tab and choose Select All from the drop down list or press Ctrl + A.                                       Note: The keyboard shortcut for copy option is         Ctrl + C.

             34                                                                                                                                                                                                                          35]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[M
 MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007                                          MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
 M


 EXITING MS WORD 2007  TEXT INSERTION

 To close MS Word 2007 application click on MS Office button and select the option Exit   To insert text in a document we can move the cursor to the desired location where the text

 Word. This option is found in the lower right corner of MS Office button. We can also Exit   is to be inserted and simply start typing. We can also insert text in a document by other
 by double clicking on MS Office button. The keyboard shortcut is ALT+F4.  methods using cut, copy and paste options. Now let us discuss the other methods.
 TEXT SELECTION  CUT OPTION

 To work or edit any text it is necessary to select a particular text that includes a word, line
           This option is used to cut a particular portion of the text and temporarily place it on the
 or a paragraph. The text can be selected in two different ways, namely
           clipboard. In other words, this option is used to move a portion of the text from one part of
 •  Using keyboard  the document to the other position in the same document or can be placed in some other

 •  Using Mouse  document too. To perform the cut option follow the steps given below.
 SELECTING TEXT WITH KEYBOARD  Step 1 :  Select the text that you wish to cut (using the Mouse or Shift + arrow key)

 This  way  of  selection  is  done  when  a  particular  word,  line  or  paragraph  has  to  be   Step 2 :  Right click and select the option Cut. Now the highlighted text is removed from
 selected. Keyboard selection is carried out by pressing the Shift key along with the             the current position and placed on the clipboard, which is a temporary storage
 appropriate arrow keys.               area.

 SELECTING TEXT WITH MOUSE  Note: The keyboard shortcut for performing the cut action is Ctrl + X . The Cut option is

 The mouse selection can be done by placing the cursor at the beginning of the text,   always followed by the Paste option.
 holding the left mouse button and dragging across the text that is to be selected. Once   PASTE OPTION
 the desired text is selected, it will be highlighted. The text can be deselected by clicking
           This option is used to insert the contents of the clipboard (contains text cut/copied) at the
 the mouse outside the selected area.
           cursor position where the desired text is required. To perform the paste option follow the
           steps given below.

           Step 1 :  Place the cursor at the position, where you want the text to be inserted.

           Step 2 : Right click on the mouse and select the option Paste. Now the selected text is
                      pasted. The keyboard shortcut for the Paste option is Ctrl + V         .
           COPY OPTION

           This option is used to make a copy of a part of the text or the whole text in the same
           document or in a different document at the cursor position. To perform the copy option
           follow the steps given below.

           Step 1 :  Select the text which you want to copy.

           Step 2 :  Right  click  on  the  mouse  and  select  the  option  copy.  Now  a  copy  of  the
                      highlighted text is placed on the clipboard, but the original text remains in the
 Note:
                      same position. The Copy option is also followed by the Paste option.
 •  To select a word double-click within the word.
           Place the cursor at the position where you want a copy of the text to be inserted (either in
 •  To select a paragraph triple-click within the paragraph.  the same document or open another document). Then right click on the mouse and select

 •  To select the entire document click on the select button located in the right corner   the option Paste. This action will paste a copy of the text at the cursor position.
 of the Home tab and choose Select All from the drop down list or press Ctrl + A.  Note: The keyboard shortcut for copy option is  Ctrl + C.

 34                                                                                                          35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                              MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                                                                                                                                              M
                                                                                        MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                                        M                                                                                            ICT


                 FILL IN THE BLANKS                                                                                                            CHOOSE THE CORRECT ANSWER

            1.  DTP stands for _____________________________                   .                                                        1. Keyboard selection is carried out by pressing the ____________                  key along

            2.  MS word 2007 was developed by ______________                  corporation.                                                 with the appropriate arrow keys.


                                                                  a
                                                                                  a
            3.  To get into MS Word 2007, click on start   programs   __________________ a                                                 (a) Shift                 (b) Control                  (c) Home
                 Microsoft office Word 2007.                                                                                            2. To select a word _____________            within the word.
            4.  _______________         is found at the top left part of the MS Word 2007 window.                                          (a) Click                 (b) Triple click             (c) Double click

            5.  _______________         toolbar help us to access the frequently used commands.                                         3. The keyboard shortcut for Save As option is  ________________                   .

            6.  Ribbon  is  a  collection  of  ____________           in  a  panel  at  the  top  portion  of  the                         (a) F10                   (b) F12                      (c) F4
                 document.                                                                                                              4. ____________       button is found at the top right corner of the document.

            7.  A horizontal scroll bar is used to scroll from ______________               to  _____________                              (a) Restore               (b) Maximize                 (c) Close

                 and vice versa.                                                                                                        5. To exit MS Word 2007 click MS Office button and select the option _________                       .
            8.  ______________         controls the margins of the page.                                                                   (a) Close                 (b) Exit Word                (c) None of these


            9.  ______________        option is used to move a text from one part of the document to                                           MATCH THE FOLLOWING
                 the other position in the same document.                                                                E              1.  Ctrl + S                 -      Redo                                                                      E

            10. The text can be _______________          by clicking the mouse outside the selected area.                               2.  Ctrl + Z                 -      Saves the document

                  TICK TRUE OR FALSE                                                                                     S              3.  Ctrl + Y                 -      Minimizing /maximizing the ribbon                                         S


            1. Word processing is integral for the preparation and                                                                      4.  Ctrl + V                 -      New blank document
               presentation of documents.                                                      True         False        I              5.  Ctrl + F4                -      Undo                                                                      I

            2. By default only two buttons appear in the quick access toolbar. True                         False        C              6.  Ctrl + F1                -      Paste                                                                     C
            3. The ribbon has nine tabs.                                                       True         False

            4. The Keyboard shortcut for minimizing/maximizing the ribbon                                                               7.  Ctrl + N                 -      Copy
               is Ctrl +F1.                                                                    True         False        R              8.  Ctrl + O                 -      Select All                                                                R

            5. The text can be selected in three different ways.                               True         False                       9.  Ctrl + A                 -      Opens a document

            6.  To select a paragraph, triple click within the paragraph.                      True         False        E              10. Ctrl + C                 -      Closes a document                                                         E
            7.  The keyboard shortcut for undo is Ctrl+Y.                                      True         False

            8.  To open a document, click on MS Office button and select                       True         False        X                     ANSWER THE FOLLOWING                                                                                   X
                the option open.                                                                                                        1.  What is a Word processor? Give few examples.

            9.  Exit word option is found in the lower left corner of the                      True         False                       2.  Write a short note on MS Office button.
                MS Office button.                                                                                        E              3.  What is Ribbon?                                                                                           E

            10. The Keyboard shortcut for closing a document is Ctrl+F4.                       True         False                       4.  Name the two types of scroll bars.

             36                                                                                                                                                                                                                          37]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                  MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                  M
 MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
 M                                                      ICT


 FILL IN THE BLANKS  CHOOSE THE CORRECT ANSWER

 1.  DTP stands for _____________________________ .  1. Keyboard selection is carried out by pressing the ____________  key along

 2.  MS word 2007 was developed by ______________  corporation.  with the appropriate arrow keys.


 a
 a
 3.  To get into MS Word 2007, click on start   programs   __________________ a  (a) Shift  (b) Control  (c) Home
 Microsoft office Word 2007.  2. To select a word _____________  within the word.
 4.  _______________  is found at the top left part of the MS Word 2007 window.  (a) Click  (b) Triple click  (c) Double click

 5.  _______________  toolbar help us to access the frequently used commands.  3. The keyboard shortcut for Save As option is  ________________ .

 6.  Ribbon  is  a  collection  of  ____________   in  a  panel  at  the  top  portion  of  the   (a) F10  (b) F12  (c) F4
 document.  4. ____________       button is found at the top right corner of the document.

 7.  A horizontal scroll bar is used to scroll from ______________  to  _____________    (a) Restore  (b) Maximize  (c) Close

 and vice versa.  5. To exit MS Word 2007 click MS Office button and select the option _________                 .
 8.  ______________  controls the margins of the page.  (a) Close  (b) Exit Word  (c) None of these


 9.  ______________ option is used to move a text from one part of the document to   MATCH THE FOLLOWING
 the other position in the same document.  E  1.  Ctrl + S  -  Redo                                                       E

 10. The text can be _______________ by clicking the mouse outside the selected area.  2.  Ctrl + Z  -  Saves the document

 TICK TRUE OR FALSE  S  3.  Ctrl + Y     -      Minimizing /maximizing the ribbon                                         S


 1. Word processing is integral for the preparation and    4.  Ctrl + V  -  New blank document
 presentation of documents.  True  False  I  5.  Ctrl + F4  -  Undo                                                       I

 2. By default only two buttons appear in the quick access toolbar. True  False  C  6.  Ctrl + F1  -  Paste               C
 3. The ribbon has nine tabs.  True  False

 4. The Keyboard shortcut for minimizing/maximizing the ribbon   7.  Ctrl + N  -  Copy
 is Ctrl +F1.  True  False  R  8.  Ctrl + O  -  Select All                                                                R

 5. The text can be selected in three different ways.  True  False  9.  Ctrl + A  -  Opens a document

 6.  To select a paragraph, triple click within the paragraph.  True  False  E  10. Ctrl + C  -  Closes a document        E
 7.  The keyboard shortcut for undo is Ctrl+Y.  True  False

 8.  To open a document, click on MS Office button and select   True  False  X  ANSWER THE FOLLOWING                      X
 the option open.  1.  What is a Word processor? Give few examples.

 9.  Exit word option is found in the lower left corner of the   True  False  2.  Write a short note on MS Office button.
 MS Office button.  E  3.  What is Ribbon?                                                                                E

 10. The Keyboard shortcut for closing a document is Ctrl+F4.  True  False  4.  Name the two types of scroll bars.

 36                                                                                                          37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[ICT
                                                                                                                                                                                     ICT
                                                                                        MS WORD 2007S WORD 2007
                                                                                        M                                                                                                             CHAPTER 4CHAPTER 4
                                                                                                                                                                        Formatting in


           5.  Differentiate Save and Save As options.
           6.  How will you close a document?                                                                                          Introduction                                           MS Word 2007

           7.  Write the steps to cut the text in a document?
                                                                                                                                       A document usually comprises primarily of text. Thus it is important for this text to be laid
           8.  What are the different ways to select text?
                                                                                                                                       out such that it is clear and legible to read.
           9.  Write any two features of MS Word 2007.
                                                                                                                                       Laying out text to make it appear organised and attractive is called Formatting. Word
           10. What is work area?                                                                                                      2007  provides  many  formatting  features  like  applying  fonts,  font  styles  and  sizes,

                 ANSWER THE FOLLOWING IN DETAIL                                                                                        paragraphing and alignment of a group of text, character and line spacing, changing
                                                                                                                                       case, bulleting and numbering etc.
           1. Explain Quick Access toolbar.

           2. Explain the different ways of text selection.                                                                             TEXT FORMATTING

                                 try                                                                                                   Applying Fonts
                                 in your                                                                                               Font is writing style or technique. MS word 2007 contains a collection of fonts, some of
                                      lab                                                                                              which are used for corporate, decorative and designing purposes. Some fonts are also

                                                                                                                                       symbolic in nature. These are used to stylize
                   1.  Create a new file and type your name and class you                                                              any writing. By applying fonts, one can make
                        are studying in                                                                                                document look more attractive.

                   2.  Create another file and type the following text:                                  E                             To  change  the  font  type,  click  on  the  font

                        "Word  processing  is  one  of  the  most  important                                                           name drop down arrow, which is found in the
                        activities carried out in a work place"                                          S                             Home tab of the ribbon. You will find a list of
                   3.  Minimize  the  currently  working  file  and  type  the                                                         fonts, which can be viewed by scrolling and

                        same in the first file.                                                          I                             you can choose the font and then start keying

                   4.  Close the first file, observe what happens.                                                                     in the text.        Use the keyboard shortcut
                   5.  Save the same file with the filename "Myfile.docx"in                              C                             Font Sizes          Ctrl + D to change the      Hint
                                                                                                                                                           font name.
                        C Drive and close it.                                                                                                                                         The  size  of  text  matters  considerably  while

                   6.  Save the second file with the filename happy.docx.                                R                                                                            formatting. The text must be large enough to

                   7.  Open the file MyFile.docx and search for text "Word                                                                                                            appear legible. Usually, font size is measured in
                        Processor "and observe what happens.                                                                                                                          points. The minimum size provided is 8 and the

                   8.  Open any of the existing file (Created by you and                                 E                                                                            maximum  size  is  72.  The  font  size  can  be
                        type the first paragraph of this chapter.                                                                                                                     changed by clicking on the font size drop down

                   9.  Save  the  file.  Copy  only  the  first  two  lines  in  the                     X                                                                            arrow and choosing the appropriate size.
                        2nd page.                                                                                                                                                                  DO  Y U  KNOW?
                                                                                                                                                                                                               O
                   10. Select all the text and move it to the 3rd page.
                   11. Select the text using keyboard and mouse.                                         E                                                                                          'Ctrl + [ '  increases the
                                                                                                                                                                                                      font size by 1 point
                   12. Exit MS Word 2007.                                                                                                                                                          and   'Ctrl + ]'   reduces the
             38                                                                                                                                                                                       font size by 1 point               39]]></page></pages></Search>
